<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Brocket Hall, before the right vvorshipfull, Sir Iohn Brocket, and other gentlemen there assembled for the trayning of souldiers</title>
            <title>Sermon preached at Brocket Hall, before the right worshipfull, Sir John Brocket, and other gentlemen there assembled for the trayning of souldiers.</title>
            <author>Harris, Edward, fl.1587-1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119766</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854972</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854972</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20439</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02671)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20439)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 569:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Brocket Hall, before the right vvorshipfull, Sir Iohn Brocket, and other gentlemen there assembled for the trayning of souldiers</title>
                  <title>Sermon preached at Brocket Hall, before the right worshipfull, Sir John Brocket, and other gentlemen there assembled for the trayning of souldiers.</title>
                  <author>Harris, Edward, fl.1587-1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Orwin, for Iohn Daldern and William Haw,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20439:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20439:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>BROCKET HALL, BEFORE</hi> the Right VVorſhipfull, Sir <hi>John Brocket, and other Gentlemen</hi> there aſſembled for the trayning <hi>of Souldiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>January 2 and 3.</p>
            <p>By Edmond Harris.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by Thomas Orwin, for Iohn Daldern and William Haw. 1588.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20439:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20439:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right VVorſhipfull <hi>Sir Iohn Brocket Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was no parte of my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (right Woorſhipfull) to haue communicated to any that which I ſpake by waie of exhortation and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the Souldiers that ſhewed themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you the 2. and 3. of <hi>Ianuary.</hi> Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I could not reſiſt the daily importunitie of my friends, deſiring to bee partakers of ſuch matter as the Lord of his mercie did at that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine miniſter vnto mee for the comfort of thé which heard. Wherefore giuing my ſelfe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what I had ſpoken, I deliuered them in writing ſo much as I could call to mind againe; which they finding meanes (I knowe not how) to bring vnto the print and certifying me ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that duetie, which for your goodne<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to me warde I owe vnto your woorſhip, cauſed me to preſent it vnto you; and ſo much the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you were the onely man; which when the
<pb facs="tcp:20439:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Souldiers were readiero come before you, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed mee to employ my ſpeache to ſuch ende and purpoſe. Wherefore I beſeech your worſhip to accept of this my ſmall preſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a teſtimonie rather of my well meaning, than a reward of your benefites. The Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in you and yours his ſpiritual graces, and preſerue you by faith working through loue vnto the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his ſonne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips to commaund in the Lord,</hi> Edmond Harris.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20439:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Dread not, neither bee a fraide of them. The Lord your God which goeth before you he ſhall fight for you, according to all that he did in Egipt before your eyes.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was my purpoſe (right woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) to haue gone forward in the expoſition of S. <hi>Peter</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I began: but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering how the occaſion of this daies meeting required other exhortations than the words which were next to be expounded would miniſter unto us, I thought good to chooſe out an other portion of Scripture, agreeable to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent matter: eſpeciallie conſidering how ſome euill diſpoſed perſons goe about to weaken the hearts and hands of our countrimen, as though we were not able to encounter with our Popiſh &amp; Spaniſh aduerſaries that now threaten us with encombe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of warre in our owne land. The Scripture which I have ſelected and choſen for this purpoſe is found written in the firſt of <hi>Deuteronomie:</hi> The wordes whereof are theſe, <hi>Dread not, &amp;c.</hi> which containe in them a propheticall exhortation, wherewith <hi>Moſes</hi> the conducter of <hi>Iſrael</hi> encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged
<pb facs="tcp:20439:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>the people of the Lord, what time they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to faint for feare of their enemies. For hauing beard ſate, how they ſhould encounter with the ſonnes of <hi>Anake</hi> men of giantlike ſtature, who did cate by the Inhabitants of the land, and in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of whome the valiant men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were but as Graſhoppers to looke too, they tooke ſo ſodaine diſcomfiture at theſe ridings, that they rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired never to ſee the promiſed land, than to ioyne battaile with ſo ſtrong and mightie aduerſaries. This <hi>Moſes</hi> perceiuing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted them with theſe wordes, faying: <hi>Dread not, &amp;c.</hi> In which ſpeech we are to obſerue theſe two braunches, whereinto the Scripture deuideth it ſelfe. Firſt, an exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Secondly, the reaſons of that exhortation. The exhortation is this, <hi>Dread not, neither bee afraide of them.</hi> The reaſons are two in number. The firſt taken from the ſauing preſence of God among his people. <hi>The Lorde your God which goeth before you, he ſhall fight for you.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond taken from their former experience and triall of Gods mightie protection to themwarde in the land of Egipt. <hi>According to all &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the exhortation, let vs obſerue who are exhorted not to feare, and whom they are exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not to feare: where the holy ghoſt ſaith, <hi>Dread not, neither bee afraide of them,</hi> he ſpeaketh to the people of God, to them that were ſanctified and ſet apart to bee a peculiar people vnto himſelfe, to
<pb facs="tcp:20439:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch as were the true profeſſors of Gods worde, thereby teaching vs, how Chriſtians ſhould not be faint harted in a good cauſe, but couragious and bould as Lyons, eſpecially when they are to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with the enemies of true religion, Neither doth <hi>Moſes</hi> alone teach vs this, but Chriſt himſelf alſo is of the ſame minde, as may appeare <hi>Math. 24. 6.</hi> For ſpeaking of thoſe troubles which ſhould come vpon the worlde in the latter age thereof, he ſaith, how <hi>They ſhould heare of warres and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of warres, but ſee that ye bee not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,</hi> ſaith he to the faithfull and beleeuing, as who ſhould ſay, that feare of the aduerſarie were not comely in them that make profeſſion of the true faith. Marke this I beſeech you brethren as many of you as feare the Lord; <hi>Moſes</hi> commaundeth ſuch not <hi>dread, neither to be afraide:</hi> Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth ſuch not to be troubled though they heare of warres, &amp;c. Now therefore as men that profeſſe the Lord to be your only ſtay and truſt, lift vp your hearts, that it may bee knowne how you haue not profeſſed in vaine, and that you are the true Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of Chriſt Jeſu, whom no force nor furniture of the enemie can feare, no rumours of warre can diſmay, no hoaſtes of armed men can once abaſh or terrifie. If your hearts bee weakened at any time with the reportes of our enemies preparation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, knowe this for a ſuretie that whenſoeuer you are diſmayd therewith, that day ye beginne to
<pb facs="tcp:20439:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>proclaime and ſhewe your ſelues men voyd of true faith. For why, ſuch as are the true people of God, by the iudgement both of <hi>Moſes</hi> and alſo of Chriſt himſ<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould not be afraide of theſe things. Nay mar<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>one thing more. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith to his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iſraelites: Be not afraide of them.</hi> Of whom doth he meane: It is manifeſt by the former verſe he vnderſtandeth the <hi>Anakins,</hi> that is to ſay, the Giants which enhabited the lande of <hi>Canaan,</hi> whom he chargeth the people of God not to feare, though they were men greater and taller than themſelues. Might not the ſchollers of <hi>Moſes</hi> feare Giants, and ſhall the ſchollers of Chriſt feare <hi>Spaniardes?</hi> Farre bee it of from the leaſt of vs (brethren) euer to feare theſe enemies of the Lord.</p>
            <p>To the intent that we may be the more coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious; let vs conſider of the reaſons which <hi>Moſes</hi> adioyneth to his exhortation. The firſt reaſon is taken from the ſauing preſence of God among his people, or from his effectuall power and ſtrong hande which he ſtretcheth ouer his Church to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his enheritance and to deſtroye the enemies thereof. <hi>The Lorde your God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes) he ſhall fight for you,</hi> therfore be not afraide of them. As if hee had ſayd, They are ſure to ouerthrowe their enemies in battaile, whoſe parte the Lorde taketh, and for whom he fighteth: The Lorde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe be fighteth for you my brethren the ſonnes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20439:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore feare not but ye ſhall haue the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie ouer them. This is a notable reaſon (deerely beloued) and much vſed in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>In the 14. <hi>of Nomb.</hi> there is a notable place pertayning to the ſame matter which is here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. For when the people ſeemed to take diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfiture by the tidings which the ſpies brought them concerning the inhabitants of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the ſpirite of the Lorde came upon <hi>Ioſua,</hi> and he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted them on this wiſe. <hi>Feare not the people of the land</hi> (ſayth <hi>Ioſua) for they are but bread for vs.</hi> And he addeth the ſame reaſon which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> vſed. Their ſhield (ſayth he) is departed from them, <hi>and the Lorde is with vs,</hi> therefore <hi>feare them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the like wordes doth the good King <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechia</hi> encourage the Captaines and Souldiers in his time, which were readie to fight the Lordes battaile againſt the blaſphemous boaſt of the proud <hi>Senacherib:</hi> as wee may reade <hi>2. Chron. 32. Be ſtrong and couragious</hi> (ſayth <hi>Ezechia) feare not, neither bee afraide for the King of Aſhur, neither for the multitude that is with him.</hi> Dis reaſon he adioyneth, <hi>There be more</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with vs thé are with thé: with him is an arme of fleſh, but with vs is the Lord our God for to help vs, &amp; to fight our battels.</hi> Conſider theſe things, my brethren; the Lord will fight for them that profeſſe his trueth, and whome he fighteth for they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:20439:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>vndoubtedly preuaile and triumph ouer their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies be they neuer ſo well prepared to the battaile. Let vs then cleaue truely and vufainedly to the Lord our God, ſo ſhall he fight for vs, and our ene. mies ſhall not be able to ſtand before vs. He that is a conſuming fire ſhall goe forth on our behalfe, and the ſtubble of <hi>Spayne</hi> ſhall bee conſumed to aſhes. The whitle winde of his preſence ſhal ſcatter them as chaffe, and his vengeance ſhall followe after and purſue them till they be vtterly deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Ye will deſire peraduenture more ſpeciall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and proofes in this caſe, ſuch as may make vs ſee, that the Lord will fight for his Church in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland (if it departe not from him) againſt all it Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh and Spaniſh aduerſaries. Hearken then to the word of our God which is true and infallible.</p>
            <p>The Lord himſelf threatneth to ſhed their blood which haue ſhed the blood of his Saints, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>Deut. 32.41.42. I will execute vengeaunce on myne enemies</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them that hate me, I will make myne ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes dronke with their blood, and my ſword ſhall eate their fleſh, for the blood of the ſlaine and of the captiue.</hi> But <hi>he will bee mercifull</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> in the ſame place) <hi>to his land and to his people.</hi> Heere you ſee plainly declared vnto you (my brethren) how the Lord threatneth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, which haue ſpilt the blood of his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people. This is the word of the Lorde, and
<pb facs="tcp:20439:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>therfore ſo ſure and certaine, that albeit heauen and earth doe paſſe, yet no one iot of this ſhall paſſe, till it be all accompliſhed and fulſilled. Conſiber then of our enemies which threaten vs at this time, and for reſiſtance of whom wee are aſſembled this day. Are they ſuch as haue ſpared the innocent and barmeleſſe members of Chriſt Jeſu? No verely. For it is notably knowne how much innocet blood the Pope our chiefe aduerſarie, and his Lieutenant the Catholique King haue ſhed in Chriſtendome. The earth which greedilie drinketh in cuery ſuch thing, is wearie with drinking vy the blood of Chriſt his ſheepe, which the wooluiſh in quiſitonrs of <hi>Spayne,</hi> and bloodthirſtie tormentors ſent out of the <hi>Romaine</hi> ſea haue ſpilt. The hiſtories are full of moſt lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table tragedies, declaring the ſauage, pea &amp; more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſtly crueltie of theſe our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries toward innumerable chriſtian people which neuer lift vp weapon againſt them, but were lead as ſillie Lambes to the ſlaughter, not once ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their mouthes againſt their bloodſuckers. What then remaineth but that the Lorde now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay them againe, according to all that they haue done to his Saincts and children, and that the worde of the almightie be fulfilled on them, which ſaith, that he will make his <hi>arrowes dronke with their blood:</hi> which kinde of ſpeech (beſide other thinges) would not bee lightly ouerpaſſed by vs, conſidering the bowe and the arrowe are weapons
<pb facs="tcp:20439:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of defence, wherewith the Lorde hath armed our nation aboue the reft. Let vs therefore bee aſſured, if wee conſecrate our ſelnes wholly to God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in this to continue the people of the Lorde, he will per for me his promiſe in ſauing this his lande, and vs his people; but deſtroying our enemies with moſt fearefull deſtruction, cauſing the arrowes of vs Engliſh men to drinke the blood, and our ſword to deuoure the fleſh of theſe perſons, who haue powred foorth the blood of his Saincts without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion as water vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ground in great aboun, dance. This the Lord will doe (if we go for ward to ſerue him) though not for our ſakes, which are but miſerable ſinners, yet for his promiſe-ſake, and for his Chriſtes ſake, whoſe name is called vpon vs.</p>
            <p>This for their acts: Let vs yet come neerer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe our enemies, and ſee what the Lord in his worde hath determined againſt them. If we looke vnto the profeſſion of thoſe which bend themſelues againſt vs, wee may finde great matter to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs withall. I ſtande not now to conſider and ſhewe vnto you, how the Lorde threatneth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally all Idolaters and ſuch as prouoke him with ſtraunge Gods (as they doe) that <hi>He will ſpende plagues vpon them; that he will beſtowe his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes vpon them, the ſword ſhal kill them with out, and feare ſhall kill them in their chambers. Deut. 32.</hi> Onely that I would haue you to note which is written by S. <hi>Iohn, Reuel. 14.8.9.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:20439:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>holy ghoſt hauing noted in the 6.7. &amp; 8. verſes the breaking foorth of the light of the goſpel, and there vpon the fall of <hi>Babilon</hi> or the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſea enſuing and following, to declare how grieuouſly the Lord would bee offended with ſuch, as after the decay of that <hi>Babiloniſh</hi> ſea by the goſpell of Chriſt, would not yeeld the inſelues obedient to the truth, but goe forward in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting idolatrie or ſpirituall fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with that whore of <hi>Babilon,</hi> whoſe ſhame full abominations the Lorde had detected before their faces by the plaine preaching of the worde, he vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth this moſt fearefull iudgement againſt them: <hi>If any man</hi> (ſaith an Angeli from heauen) <hi>worſhip the beaſt and his image, and receiue the marke in his forehead or on his hand,</hi> (that is, either o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly ſhewe himſelfe a maintainer of that <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſea, or ſecretly ſubſcribe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abominations therof) <hi>The ſame ſhall drinke of the wine of the wrath of God, yea of the pure wine which is powred into the cup of his wrath; &amp; he ſhall be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in fire &amp; brimſtone before the holy Angels &amp; before the Lambe.</hi> Weigh this aduiſedly with your ſelues my brethren for to encourage you with all. Ye know that the goſpell hath now along time bene preached a freſh in the worlde, &amp; <hi>Babilon</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Romaine</hi> ſea hath taken a great fall therby, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we ſee that they which now threaten vs with warre and trouble, ſticke ſtil to that whore of <hi>Babilon,</hi> they ſtill worſhippe the beaſt and his
<pb facs="tcp:20439:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Image the Popedome, they delight to ſhe we them ſelues and write themſelues Papiſts, they will not bee drawne from the breaſtes of that harlot, which the reſt of Chriſtendome abhorreth as a moſt <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſtrumpet, and as the mother of all Idolatrie and ſpirituall fornication, they delight ſtill more in her painted falſhood than in the true and glorious beautie of the ſpoaſe of Chriſt Ieſu: what remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth therefore (deerely beloued) for theſe popiſh ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of ours, but that they ſhall drinke of the wine of the wrath of God: that is to ſay, God will take bengeaunce on them in moſt terrible maner. Yea, but ſhall we be the inſtruments of the Lordes wrath againſt them, ſhall they be deſtroyed by vs, will ſome ſay: Although it ſkilleth not whether they be deſtroyed by vs or for vs, yet marke what is written <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17. 16. 17. The Kings which firſt gaue their kingdome to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beaſt, but after ward <hi>fell to hate the whore, they ſhal make her deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and naked.</hi> They ſhall deprine her both of pourpe and power, and ſhall leaue her ſuccourleſſe and friendleſſe in compariſon. Haue not wee (bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) ſometimes committed fornication with that Romiſh harlot, but doe wee not now hate her as much as euer we loued her; it is then greatly to be hoped, that if wee continue to hate her ſtill withall her whoriſh tromperies and ſuperſtitions, we <hi>ſhall be the meanes of the Lord to make her vtterly deſolate,</hi> by ouerthrowing theſe her onely defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants,
<pb facs="tcp:20439:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>or by helping thereto.</p>
            <p>This comfort and hope to preuaſle wee haue by our enemies that threaten to aſſaile vs; let vs ſee whether any comfort and courage be miniſtred, by reaſon of thoſe which are meanes to ſet them on and exhorte them to this aſſault. We doe all of vs knowe (deerely beloued) how the Embaſſadours which prouoke and ſtirre vp theſe and other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res againſt vs are thoſe rouing Jeſuits, which ſent from the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> creepe euery where into Kings courts, exhorting both them and their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie againſt vs. Hath the Scripture then deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined what euent their counſailes ſhall haue, to what ende the Princes which are ruled by them ſhall come vnto: Yea verely: looke <hi>Reuel.</hi> 16. and you ſhall find it ſet downe there. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> verſe 12. of that chapter hauing (vnder the figure of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates</hi> dried vp, by which meanes the olde <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> was deſtroyed) propheſied the deſtruction of the <hi>Romiſh Babilon,</hi> he ſaith in the 13. verſe, that <hi>He ſawe three vncleane ſpirites like frogges come out of the mouth of that drakon, and out of the mouth of that beaſt, &amp; out of the mouth of that falſe Prophet:</hi> The office of theſe frogges be deſcribeth to bee this, <hi>to gather the Kings of the earth to the battell of that great day of God almightie.</hi> Meaning y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their purpoſe ſhould be to ſtirre vp the Kings againſt the deſtroyers of their <hi>Babilonian</hi> tower, and to bring them to build
<pb facs="tcp:20439:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>it againe, if it might be, but the Lord ſhould other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſpoſe their labours, and himſelfe take the cauſe of his children in hand, making battaile with them, &amp;c. The whole difficultie of this place lyeth in knowing who are ment by theſe frogges. Some vnderſtand the Popiſh ſchoolemen: but that cannot bee. Firſt, becauſe the Prophet noteth how theſe frogges ſhould not come foorth till the decay and way made to the ouerthrowe of their <hi>Babilon;</hi> as for the ſchoolemen they were in the flouriſhing ſtate of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Monarchie. Secondly, it was not the office of the Popiſh ſchoolemen to go from one countrie to an other, from one Prince to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to ſtirre them vp againſt the people of the Lorde: but theſe properties both of them agree to the Jeſuites and to them only. For after the decay of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſupremacie they were inuented for this entent, that they might go from one King and Kingdome to an other, ſtirring them to battaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the decayers of their <hi>Babilon;</hi> And wee ſee that they haue not bene ſluggiſh nor negligent in doing this. It is then out of all doubt and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, that the Jeſuits are ment by thoſe frogges. What then ſhalbe the euent of the labours of theſe Jeſuites: They ſhall gather the Kings (to battell againſt the Lord) to aplace, ſaith S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> called in Debrew <hi>Har Mageddon,</hi> the mountaine of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geddo</hi> or <hi>Megiddo,</hi> a place famous by reaſon of great ſlaughter there committed, meaning that
<pb facs="tcp:20439:9"/>they ſhall gather them to their owne deſtruction as the whole text manifeſtly declareth. This ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth greatly for our encouragement (deerely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued). The Princes which threaten vs are gathered by theſe Jeſuits, not ſo much againſt vs as againſt the Lord himſelfe, whoſe word we truely profeſſe: therefore (if our iniquities and lacke of following our profeſſion doe not make ſeparation betwixt vs and the helping hand of God) the ende of thoſe Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitiſh embaſſadours councell ſhall come vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that is, their gathering together ſhall bee to their owne deſtruction: for the Lorde will fight againſt them.</p>
            <p>I will adde but this one reaſon for the perticuler perſons, and I beſeech you be are with me, if I be the longer in it, conſidering it poynteth out the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie time wherein we liue, and containeth our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries by name. The place is written <hi>Reuel.</hi> 20. where it is ſayd, that <hi>Gog and Magog ſhall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther themſelues to battell, and ſhall compaſſe the tents of the Saincts about and the beloued citie, &amp;c.</hi> For the more plaine vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding wher, of, I muſt needes declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaning of that which goeth before in that chapter, and alſo of ſomewhat in the 12. which hath relation to the 20. In the 12 chapter of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> after that Chriſt was aſcended verſe the 5. and the woman which is the Church, deliuered by flight from the Dragon, the Dragon went and made warre with the remnant
<pb facs="tcp:20439:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>of her ſeede which keepe the commaundements of GOD and haue the teſtimonie of Jeſus Chriſt: whereby is ſignified that Sathan ſhould raiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt the true Chriſtians, which was fulfilled in thoſe tenne perſecutions vnder the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> Empire, which ended <hi>Anno domini 367.</hi> Here S. <hi>Iohn</hi> leaueth to ſpeake of the dragon, and ſpeaketh no more of him all the 20. chapter, where be beginneth at the time whereat he left before. As if one ſhould demaunde of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> what became of the drakon after thoſe perſecutions, he aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from the end of thoſe perſecutions to the terme of a thouſand yeeres more the deuill ſhall be bound up, meaning that be ſhould not raiſe any ſuch open perſecution againſt the Church for the faith, it might vee demaunded then what ſhould become of ſuch as were ſtaine in thoſe perſecutions. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> aunſwereth verſe 4. they ſhall line and raigne with Chriſt al that thouſand yeeres. Some might aſ ke againe: what ſhall bee the ſtate of the people from that yeere 367. to the end of thoſe thouſand yeres. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> aunſwereth, They ſhalbe dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes euery day more &amp; more through the ignorance of the trueth of Gods word, but at the end of thoſe thouſand yerrs they ſhal reuiue againe. With what reſurrection ſhal they reuiue? ſhal their bodies the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> riſe out of the graue. No, ſaith <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> they ſhall liue againe by the firſt reſurruction, or ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the man from ſinne: for at the ende of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:20439:10"/>thouſand yeres. <hi>1. Anno domini 1367.</hi> the goſpel ſhall breake forth againe, (and in doe de then <hi>VVick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiffe</hi> began to preach) and men ſhall reuiue againe by the meanes of the true preaching of the worde that then ſhall be.</p>
            <p>Some might further aſke, what ſhall Sathan then bée bound vp ſtill after this time of one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeeres expired, that is after the yeere 1367: S. <hi>Iohn</hi> aunſwereth, no; but he ſhall bee looſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſhall fall to perſecuting of the truth then preached, which perſecution ſhal laſt for a little ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. verſe 3. After all this (to come now vnto our ſelues) it might bee demaunded by whom Sathan ſhould perſecute the profeſſors of the trueth that ſhort time, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> aunſwereth by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> whome hee ſhould at the laſt ſtirre vp to make warre againſt the Saincts. Ye ſee now we are come (deerely beloued) vnto our owne time. The Goſpell which lay hidde as it were till the yeere 1367. than began to ſhine foorth againe by the preaching of <hi>Wickleife,</hi> ſince that time which is but a ſhorte ſpace in compariſon the profeſſors of the Goſpell haue bene perſecuted: now <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> make warre againſt the true profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Chriſtianitie. Who are meant, will ſome ſay, by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog.</hi> Concerning <hi>Gog,</hi> looke <hi>Ezech. 38.</hi> and 39. and there you ſhall ſee that <hi>Gog</hi> is called the Prince of <hi>Meſech and Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball:</hi> by which <hi>Tuball</hi> are vnderſtood the <hi>Italians</hi>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20439:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20439:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:20439:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>Spaniardes</hi> (as the learned may ſee in <hi>Iohn Funcius</hi> his diuiſion of the world in his chronicle) by <hi>Meſech</hi> the <hi>Turkes,</hi> by <hi>Magog</hi> the <hi>Tartarians,</hi> and wee doe all of vs knowe, that theſe are they which at this time doe perſecute Chriſtianitie, the <hi>Turkes</hi> in the Caſt Church, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talians</hi> in the Weſt and North partes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. We ſee then who are <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> as alſo that our enemies which warre againſt vs, that is to ſay, the <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniardes</hi> are a parte of them; what comforte haue wee by this, or how doth this put vs out of feare by ſhewing that the Lord will fight for vs; that which followeth in the text will ſtrengthen vs in the Lord. For the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ghoſt telleth vs plainly, that <hi>Gog Magog ſhall compaſſe the tentes of the Saincts about, but fire</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>came downe from GOD out of heauen and deuoured them. verſe.</hi> 9. Whereby is meant either that God will plague, puniſh and deſtroy them with moſt terrible indgements from heauen, according to the phraſe of the. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Pſal. 18.12.13.14. Pſal. 11.6.</hi> Or els that the laſt iudgement ſhall come vpon them, and take them in their wickedneſſe, &amp; whileſt they are war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the Saincts and people of God: both which are of force and ſufficient to encourage vs. For if the Lorde will fight for vs with vengeance from heauen againſt our enemies, againſt the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> by name (which are a
<pb facs="tcp:20439:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>parte of <hi>Gog.</hi>) what more auaileable to encourage vs againſt them. Or els if the Lord will haſten his indgement, and for the ſaluation and deliuetance of his people, whom <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> hath compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Saincts about to deſtroy them, wil oppreſſe them with that reuenging fire which ſhall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie that laſt iudgement of his: what can bee a greater conſolation then this, that our brethren whereſoeuer and we ſhall not long fight and ſtriue againſt theſe enemics of ours, before the day of indgement ſhall come and vtterly deſtroy them. <hi>O my brethren, I beſeech you in the name of Chriſt Ieſu,</hi> let vs not once faint nor be afraide, ye ſee the times agree, the enemies are named, the trouble is begunne (in ſome places a good while ſince (let vs not doubt but the Lorde which neuer deceiueth will performe his promiſe in due time, &amp; take vengeance on our enemics. In y meane ſeaſon let vs be couragious for our people, for our true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, &amp; for the cities of our God, &amp; let <hi>the Lord do that which is good in his eyes. 2. Sam. 10.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the perſons hetherto, let vs now weigh the comfort and conſolation which we haue by the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for which they aſſayle vs, and in confidence wherof we prepare and addreſſe our ſelues againſt them. It appeareth (deerely beloued) by that which is written <hi>Iud. 20.</hi> how they which ſet vppon any to deſtroy them ſhould haue a good cauſe, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they cannot hope and looke for the helpe and
<pb facs="tcp:20439:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>aſſiſtance of the almightie: The reſt of the Tribes when they make themſelues readie to battaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Behiamites,</hi> it is for want of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and puniſhing of men which had committed moſt ſhamefull and deteſtable filthineſſe with <hi>a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites</hi> wife, neither that alone but moreouer had murdered her by that meanes. Haue our enemies any ſuch cauſe of warring againſt vs: Uerely no. Wherefore then are they gathered together, wherefore doe they threaten Fire and Sworde? There is no doubt whatſoeuer bee pretended; the ſetting vp againe of their <hi>Romiſh</hi> religion, the ſuppreſſing of the Goſpell now preached among vs, the ſatiſfying of the bloodthirſtie minde of their proude Pops is altogether entended by this warre of theirs. This ought then to turne vnto our comforte, and ſetting all feare a parte to cauſe vs vnder hope of the Lorde his helpe and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to goe with couragious heartes againſt them.</p>
            <p>They aſſault to driue vs from the the Lorde, wee defende that wee may not bee ſeperated from him: they fight to bereaue vs of the true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the worde the onely comforte of our ſoules, wee ſtriue to keepe, continue, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaſe it amongſt vs: they bende themſelues to fulfill the minde of Antichriſt, wee withſtande to accompiſh the minde of Chriſte: They warre to bring Poperie the ſtucke of all ſedition and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:20439:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>amongſt vs, wee reſiſt to keepe it out, and to retaine trueth the mother of peace and godlineſſe ſtill in the lande: Thus they fight for an euill, wee for a good cauſe. Then let vs boldly fight this battaile of the Lorde. For ſeeing they doe not come out againſt our Soueraigne and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Countrie for any <hi>Euill that they haue founde in them, but onely riſe vp to perſecute vs and to ſeeke our ſoules</hi> for profeſſing the trueth, and doing after that which is right and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, let vs not doubt but <hi>The ſoules of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne and of her people are bounde vp in the bundle of life with the Lorde their God, and that GOD will caſt out the ſoules of our enemies as out of the middle of a Sling. 1. Sam. 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember that worthic exhortation of Jeſus the ſonne of Sirach chap. 4. of his booke. <hi>Striue</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>for the trueth vnto death, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend iuſtice for thy life, and the Lord God ſhall fight for thee againſt thine enemies.</hi> For why his delight is to defende his trueth, and he taketh pleaſure in maintayning the good cauſe of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and choſen people.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſo: Conſider I beſeech you (deerely beloued) the moſt comfortable examples of the holy Scripture, written for this entent and purpoſe, that wee being preſſed in like caſe might haue hope to preuaile and ouercome in like maner.
<pb facs="tcp:20439:14"/>Although the Lorde in great mercie hath ſowne our land both with men and cattle, he hath taught our handes to warre and our fingers to fight: he hath not bene to vs as an heath or a drie vnfruitfull grounde, but hath bleſſed vs plentifully with all things neceſſarie for our defence and the withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of our enemies. Yet ſuppoſe that it were not ſo. Let it be that wee were but fewe and our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries many in number, ſhould that diſmay vs which profeſſe the trueth: God forbid. Did not <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> with 318. men of his owne houſe and no more, follow after and purſue foure wicked Kings with their whole retinue, and came home againe from the ſlaughter of them with ſafetie? <hi>Gene.</hi> 14. Did not <hi>Ioſua</hi> with a ſmall hoaſt in compariſon ſubdue and vtterly deſtroy 31. Kings and all their people? <hi>Ioſua.</hi> 12. Did not <hi>Barake</hi> hauing at his feete but tenne thouſand men ouerthrowe <hi>Siſera,</hi> his nine hundred Charets of yron, and all his hoaſt with the edge of the ſword? <hi>Iudg.</hi> 4. Did not <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> with foure hundred men alone ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hoaſt of the <hi>Amalakites,</hi> and ſmot them from the twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light euen vnto the euening of the next morowe, ſo that there eſcaped not a man of them ſaue foure hundred yong men which rodde upon Camels and fied? 1. <hi>Sam. 30.27.</hi> Did not <hi>Adino</hi> a counſailer to King <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtay himſelfe eight hundred at one time? Did not <hi>Eleazar</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Dodo,</hi> one of the three worthies of <hi>Dauid</hi> defie the <hi>Philiſtines</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20439:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>his owne ſelfe, did he not ariſe and finite the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> till his haud was wearie and claue vnto the ſworde, by whoſe meanes the Lord gaue ſo greate victorie that ſame day that the people returned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him not to fight but onely to ſpoyle? Did not three of the Captaines of the ſame <hi>Dauid</hi> when he longed to drinke of the water of the well of <hi>Bethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> breake into the hoaſt of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> that was there, and drewe water out of the well and brought it to <hi>Dauid?</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. Let it bee that there were amongſt vs neither ſpeare nor ſhield, nor any weapon of warre, ſhould wee therefore ſhrincke backe at the fight and aſſaulting of theſe our Popiſh aduerſaries? GOD forbid? Did not <hi>Shamgar</hi> with no better weapon then an Oxe goad deſtroy <hi>600.</hi> of the vncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtines</hi> and ſo deliuer <hi>Iſrael? Iudg.</hi> 3. Did not three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred perſans and no more vnder the conducting of <hi>Gedeon,</hi> by blowing the Trompets which they held in one hand and breaking the flaming pitchers which they held in the other, diſcomfite the hoaſt of the <hi>Midianites? Iudg.</hi> 7. Did not the Lorde with the ſounde of Rammes hornes and the ſhowte of mens voyces ouerthrow the high and huge walles of <hi>Hiericho? Ioſua.</hi> 6. Did not <hi>Ionathan</hi> with his armour bearer alone (what time the people of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> had neither ſword nor ſpeare among them to helpe withall) ſet vppon the mightie hoaſt of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> and ouerthrewe them? 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. Let
<pb facs="tcp:20439:15"/>vs not feare then, a ſmall companie of the houſe of faithfull <hi>Abraham</hi> will ſcrue to put foure Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Kings to flight: one <hi>Ioſua</hi> will be enough to ſubdue 31. Princes of <hi>Canaan:</hi> Euery <hi>Adino</hi> will kill his eight hundred: One <hi>Eleazar</hi> will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome the whole hoaſt himſelfe, &amp;c. An Oxe goad were weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enough in the hand of one faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Shamgar to</hi> kill 600. popiſh <hi>Philiſtines</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: An Aſſe iaw will ſerue the <hi>Nazarite</hi> of the Lord to ſtay a thouſand of them. Neither thinke (deerely beloved) that theſe are ſuch extraordinary examples as we may not hope in ſome meaſure to match the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our ſelues. For the promiſe of the Lord is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to the godly and faithfull which warre in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his truth. <hi>Fine of you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall chaſe an hundred, and an hundred of you ſhall put tenne thouſand to flight. Leuit.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>Though wee faile in theſe outward things, yet there is a notable palce in the ſecond of <hi>Daniel</hi> ſeruing to the great comfort of Chriſtian men, and ſuch as haue renounced the truſt and confidence in man to followe Chriſt Jeſu alone. The Prophet expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the viſion of <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> ſheweth how by the foure formed Image were vnderſtood ſoure Monartchies of the worlde: as by the head of golde, the <hi>Chaldean</hi> Empire: by the breaſt and armes of ſiluer, the <hi>Perſian</hi> kingdome: by the belly and thighes of braſſe, the <hi>Maccdonian</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie: by the legges of yron with feete partly of yron
<pb facs="tcp:20439:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>and partly of clay, the Empire of the <hi>Romaines:</hi> which, as yron breaketh in peeces and ſubdueth all things, ſo ſhould that ouercome and ſubdue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Monarchies of the world, and be the laſt of the ſoure. After this, ſaith <hi>Daniel,</hi> where as a ſtone cut out of the mountaine without hands ſmot the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage vpon his feete and brake them to peeces and deſtroyed all, the meaning is (ſaith the Prophet) that the kingdome of Chriſt ſhall ſubdue the laſt or <hi>Romaine</hi> Monarchie, and in that all the reſt: as for the kingdome of Chriſt it ſhal endure and ſtand for euer, by the kingdome of Chriſt not vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the perſon of Chriſt alone, but referring that worde to the whole bodie of his Church alſo. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, let vs meditate on this to our comfort: wee make no queſtion nor doubt but that wee are of the Church and kingdom of Chriſt, after whoſe name wee deſire to be called (not Catholiques) but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and wee aſſuredly truſt that wee are ſo, as many of vs as doe faithfully belecue the Goſpell now truely preached among vs. What then remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth (deerely beloued) but that we aſſure our ſelues how the kingdome of Chriſt, whereof we are, <hi>ſhall neuer bee deſtroyed, but ſhall become a greate mountaine, and fill the whole earth,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> faith. We ſee (brethren) the moſt parte of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie fulfilled, the 4. Monarchies deſtroyed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell ſet vp and preuailing euery day more &amp; more, the núber of true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s cuery where encreaſing
<pb facs="tcp:20439:16"/>euen vnder the Croſſe; let vs not then doubt of the ende of theſe beginnings, to wit, that Chriſt ſhall preuaile more gloriouſly euery day by his Church, till it hath brought the remnants of that laſt and <hi>Romaine</hi> Empire (whereof our enemies y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs are in a maner the ſumme) to vtter and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall deſolation. For Chriſt in his Church and kingdome (that the Scripture may bee fulfilled) muſt needes triumph ouer the <hi>Romaine</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie and the adherents thereof. Some will ſay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture: why, the Papiſtes alſo and our enemies ſay as much for themſelues, they boaſt how they are the Church of Chriſt, and Popedome Chriſtes kingdome, wherefore nothing letteth but that this may ſerue their turnes as well as ours. The aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is eaſie (deerely beloued) Papiſtes are not of Chriſtes kingdome. The reaſon is manifeſt, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes kingdome is appoynted to ſubdue as al other, ſo the <hi>Romaine</hi> Monarchie and Empire whether the beaſt or image of the beaſt: doe the Papiſtes fulfill this? Nay cleane contrarie they with their Pope and Catholike King doe all that they can to reſtore it, and to bring againe that <hi>Romaine</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, which Chriſt by his Church hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, into euery corner of the world. Will the kingdome of Chriſt labour to build vp that which the kingdome of Chriſt hath deſtroyed? No verely; but whatſoevuer they bee which goe about that (as out Popiſh and Spaniſh aduerſaries doe) they are
<pb facs="tcp:20439:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>out of all queſtion of the kingdome of Antichriſt. To conclude therefore and to make an ende of this reaſon; the kingdome of Chriſt (wherof are as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as profeſſe and practiſe the ſubſtance of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion truely, and whereof no Papiſtes are) ſhall bruſe the <hi>Romaine</hi> Monarchie in peeces, till it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>like the chaffe of the ſommer flowers, and the winde carie it away, that no place be found for it any more, ſaith the</hi> Prophet <hi>Daniel;</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it muſt needes followe that they and all the eudeuours of them which labour to reſtore and ſet vp againe that <hi>Romaine</hi> ſuprematic ſhall come to nought. I reaſon not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner how theſe things ſhall be done; it is enough for vs, to know that God will ſet vp Chriſtes kingdome, and make that it ſhall triumph, eſpecially ouer the <hi>Romaine</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie and defenders thereof, or any that labour to reſtore it, as theſe our aduerſaries doe.</p>
            <p>Thus ye ſee (deerely beloued) how the Lorde will fight for his ſeruants and by them; that he will fight againſt them that haue ſhed the blood of his children, as theſe our enemies haue done; that he will powre his vengeance vpon the adherents of the whore of <hi>Babilon,</hi> by the hand of thoſe which hate her, as I truſt all true Engliſh men do; that he will fight againſt them that are gathered againſt his Church at the prouocation of thoſe croking Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites; that he will fight from heauen with fire and moſt terrible iudgements againſt <hi>Gog</hi> &amp; <hi>Magog,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20439:17"/>whereof theſe our enemies are a part, as I ſhewed you. Wherefore all theſe things conſidered and thought vpon crie vnto vs; feare them not, becauſe the Lord which goeth before vs he wil fight for vs, eſpecially ſo manifold cauſes, wherein he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to helpe his, being added,</p>
            <p>Some Papiſtes will obiect peraduenture: Nay, but the Lorde he goeth before your enemies, and therefore ye cannot ſtande. Let vs therefore ſee what that phraſe employeth, to the entent we may bee aſſured whether the Lorde goe before them or vs: and ſo couſequently may bee farre of from fearing them as becommeth the true children of God.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Mofes</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lorde goeth before them,</hi> he meaneth that he was their guide by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were conducted, their Captaine whom they followed, and vnder whoſe banner they warred, which therefore would faue and defende his faith full Souldiers. Doth this agree to the religion of theſe our enemies: No verely. Why ſo: Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reaſon (deerely beloued) and you will eaſely finde it.</p>
            <p n="1">1 They which will in no wiſe be content, vnleſſe they may haue a mortall man goe before them in the perſon of Chriſt, and as his pretended Uicar in their Church, they ſhewe that the Lord himſelfe goeth not before them: for what abſurditie were it to haue a Liuetenant or Uicar where the Prince
<pb facs="tcp:20439:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>himſelfe is not onely in preſence, but moleouer ſupplieth the office of going before his people. Pet this doe our aduerſaries: for albeit Chriſt continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally goe before his Church and people in his owne perſon, yet they will not bee content vnleſſe they may haue an ydolatrous perſon vnder the name of his Uicar bee their guide and goe before them in their Church: which declareth that the Lorde Jeſu Chriſt himſelfe goeth not before them. For then what needed a Uicar exerciſing ſuch authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, if the Lord himſelfe fulfill the office and goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them in his owne perſon.</p>
            <p>Adde hercuuto that they pray vnto Sainctes, deûring them to pray vnto the Lorde for them; which were both needleſſe and fooliſh, if it were ſo that the ſame Lorde which calleth all his ſaith full vnto himſelfe and not to the Sainctes, were preſent and went before their Church and enery member thereof, as wee deleeue be doth his true Church and euery member of it.</p>
            <p>For what a ſtraunge matter were it to deſire a Sainct, which is farre of, and whereof one hath no ſureite that hee heares him, to ſpeake in his behalfe vnto the Lorde, who ſtandeth by him and goeth immediatly before him that praieth, hearing his ſuite.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Moreouer, the Scripture is plaine which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs that there is no agreement betweene God and Beliall, with Chriſt and an ydoll, ſo that there
<pb facs="tcp:20439:18"/>is no doubt but he withdraweth his preſence where the idoll is adummced, and goeth not before them before whome the idoll goeth. Conſider than of out enemies (deetely veloued) doe not they carric before them the ydolatrous hoaſt or maſſe-cake, yea as the Iſraelites ſayde to their golden calfe, <hi>Theſe are thy Gods, O Iſraell, which brought thee vp out of the land of AEgypt,</hi> do not they ſay in like manner to their breaden God, <hi>This is our very Sauiour O ye Catholiques, which died for vs and deliuered vs from hell and damnation?</hi> foraſmuch then as that filthie Idoll goeth before them, it is apparant that Chriſt our Lord, who can not agree nor will not ioyne with Idols, goeth not before them; that he conducteth them not, and that they fight not vnder his banner.</p>
            <p>As for vs (brethren) we knowe and feele the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall preſence of Chriſt our Lorde to bee ſuch to vs ward, ſo mightie, ſo auaileable, that we neither deſire a viſible Uicar generall, nor flie to inuiſible Saincts; wee abhorre and deteſt their idolatrous Paſſe, withall the whoriſh attire thereof; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truſt that our Lord he goeth before vs (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if we flie from all other things which may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unke him to forſake vs) and that he will fight for vs, in ſuch forte that we ſhall not neede to feare our enemies.</p>
            <p>Let vs come to the ſecond reaſon of <hi>Moſes</hi> er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortation, which (as I ſhewed you before) is taken
<pb facs="tcp:20439:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>from their former tryall of Gods protection in the land and deliuerance out of the land of <hi>AEgipt;</hi> or is grounded vpon the right vſe of Gods benefites and deliuerances, which his children afore time haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. for verely, God therefore deliuered his people at one time, that they hauing thereby erpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of his good will and power, might by faith reſort vnto him another time, and truſt to his helpe and aſſiſtance, and receiuing helpe praiſe him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. That I may not vee tedious vnto you in this poynt, I will bring one example and proofe, which for the cleere euidence thereof may ſerue in ſteade of many.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>1. Sam. 17.</hi> there was a notable combate towarde betweene <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Goliath;</hi> the holie Ghoſt deſcribeth both the champions (that men ſeeing how great a Giant was vanquiſhed by ſo weake a perſon, might not truſt in force of man but in the Lorde) as for example, <hi>Goliath was a man of great ſtature, Dauid</hi> but a little one; <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liath</hi> was grimme and rough, <hi>Dauid</hi> ruddie and tender; <hi>Goliath</hi> had armour and bootes of braſſe, <hi>Dauid</hi> could not beare any; <hi>Goliath</hi> was armed with a mightie ſhield and a ſpeare like a Weauers beame, <hi>Dauid</hi> had nothing but a ſling and a ſtone at the brooke in it. When <hi>Saule</hi> ſame this vnequal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the match, he goeth about to withdrawe Dauid from the combate, as one that in his indge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſure to fall before his enemie. <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20439:19"/>with an inuincible courage aunſweteth againe in the preſence of the King, &amp; to prooue that the Lord would fight for him and giue him the victorie ours his aduerſarie; he prooueth it by the former triall which he had of Gods defence and protection to him warde, on this wiſe: <hi>Thy ſeruant, O King</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) kept his fathers ſheepe, and there came a Lyon and likewiſe a Beare and tooke a ſheepe out of the flocke, and I went out after him &amp; ſmot him, &amp; tooke it out of his mouth, and when he roſe againſt me, I caught him by the beard and ſmot him and ſlew him, ſo thy ſeruant ſlewe both the Lyon &amp; the Beare,</hi> what doth he conclude herevpon. Uerely, from this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and triall he reaſoneth in this ſorte. <hi>The Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which deliuered me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pawe of the Lyon and from the pawe of the Beare, he ſal deliuer me from the hand of this Philiſtin.</hi> By the former protection of God againſt the Lyon and the Beare, he aſſureth himſelfe and prcoueth that be would alſo deliuer him from the vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed <hi>Philiſtine.</hi> So in like maner (déerely beloued) the triall which we haue had hertofore of Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linering of vs from theſe &amp; ſuch like enemies ought to be ſo many aſſurances to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare God, that the Lord will now alſo deliuer vs and veſtroy them, if wee humble ourſelues vnder the mightie hand of the Lorde, and ovey him. Let vs therefore conſider what the Lord of late hath done for vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20439:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Firſt, when the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was here in the daies of <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> and had both occaſion giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to worke vpon, knowing that our gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, the enemie of their popiſh religion, ſhould ſucceede her ſiſter, and alſo had friends enough to further their purpoſe, the moſt of the Realme at that time being Popiſhly enclined and giuen; did not the Lorde euen then deliuer vs from theſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of ours when they were in this Realme and had more friends, and ſhall he not now deliuer vs when they are out of the Realme, and haue leſſe friends by hundred thouſands amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 12. yere of her Maieſties raigne, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Guiſians of France &amp; Spaniards</hi> together wrought a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motion here in our own land, making therby a way to their deuiliſh purpoſe againſt this realm &amp; countrie of ours, did not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſuppreſſe their endeuors, &amp; diſapoynt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſauing vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their hands, who thought to haue embrewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our blood? The Lord which ſaued vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe enemies at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time, he ſhall likewiſe preſerue vs now &amp; at all times hereafter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame, ſo long as we returne not to the Romiſh &amp; heathniſh abhommations, but haue care to followe that truth which we profeſſe.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, when <hi>Campion</hi> &amp; his complices of late daies practiſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bringing in of for rain power, the deſtruction of our Prince &amp; countrie, did not the Lord ouerthrow all their practiſes &amp; ſaue vs! why ſhould wee then diſtruſt of our deliuerance at this
<pb facs="tcp:20439:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>time alſo, if we continue and goe forward to walke with the Lord. Let vs therfore conclude: The Lord which goeth before vs he will ſaue vs from theſe our enemies, according to all that he hath done for vs againſt them heretofore of his mercie and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>To theſe conſolations, there is ſomewhat that being caſt in and muttered by Popiſh ſpitites or ſuch like, may ſeeme to haue ſome force and abilitie to diſcourage weakelings, wherevnto for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome aunſwer is neceſſarie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they put in mens heads that our enemies are politique, and therefore muſt needes preuayle. I aunſwere, ſo was <hi>Ahitophell</hi> the counſailor of <hi>Dauid,</hi> yea ſo politique, that when one had aſked councell of <hi>Ahitophell,</hi> it was as if he had aſked councell at the Dracle of God himſelfe, in ſuch eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was that man for his policie both with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> and all the people: notwithſtanding, when he employed his policie to worke vngodlineſſe, and to ſet vp the ambitious and wicked <hi>Abſalom</hi> and to put downe the godly <hi>Dauid,</hi> the Lord turned his councell into fooliſhneſſe. <hi>2. Sam. 17.</hi> So brethren, let vs aſſure our ſelues, that for as much as their whole policie tendeth to the aduancement of ſome wicked <hi>Abſalom,</hi> the depoſing of our faithful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, and the working of wickedneſſe, the Lord will turne it into fooliſhneſſe and deſtroy it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which is ſaide <hi>Iob. 5.12.13.15. The
<pb facs="tcp:20439:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lorde ſcattereth the deuiſes of the craftie, ſo that their hands cannot accompliſh that which they doe enterpriſe: He taketh the wiſe in their craftineſſe, and the councell of the wicked is made fooliſh. But he ſaueth the poore from the ſword, from their mouth, and from the hand of the violent man.</hi> Moreouer, for as much (deerely beloued) as they bend their whole policie to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowing of our profeſſion and religion, let vs not bee any whit afraide of their politique heades. For why, to vſe policie againſt the trueth is to vſe it againſt the Lorde himſelfe, againſt whome no councell can proſper, as it is ſaide, <hi>Prouerb. 21. There is no councell, there is no wiſedom, there is no vnderſtanding againſt the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An other thing there is which ſomewhat moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thoſe that put not their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in the Lord, which is this, becauſe they ſee our enemies ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to miſchiefe, that they addreſſe themſelues to meete vs and come vnto vs in our owne countrie. For aunſwer herevnto, it is a moſt notable hiſtorie and moſt fit in this caſe, which wee finde written <hi>2. Reg. 9.</hi> Declaring how the Lord is wont many times to render blood againe in that place where blood hath bene ſhed: As for example, <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Ieſebell</hi> his wife ſhed the blood of <hi>Naboth</hi> in the field of the ſame <hi>Naboth,</hi> it was therefore the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lorde that there the blood of <hi>Ieſebell</hi> and of <hi>Ahabs</hi> ſonne ſhould be ſhed againe. This
<pb facs="tcp:20439:21"/>was <hi>Iehu</hi> appointed to execute, who when he went about it, <hi>Iehoram</hi> by the ſecret worke of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the firſt in another place, met him in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field, &amp; there was ſlaine: conſider then with your ſelues (deerely beloued) who are now ſayd to come out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs; are they not men ſent from the Pope and King of <hi>Spayne?</hi> Were not the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in this Realme, in the daies of <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> partakers in the ſhedding of the blood of Gods children: for might not their Catholike King haue wrought the preſeruation of theſe Martirs, was not his conſent and theirs in the making and playing of that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie, was not the <hi>Italian Nimrod</hi> the chiefe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of that bloodſhed: What then may wee thinke (deerely beloued) concerning their entent of aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs here in this lande: Uerely (if wee goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to feare the Lord) there is great hope that the Lorde hath hardned their hearts, and put in their mindes to come hether, to the entent he might here requite them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> blood again, who were in this place partakers in the ſhedding of the blood of his ſaincts.</p>
            <p>Thus I haue ſhortly (my bretheren) ſhewed you, according as this portion of Scripture gaue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, with what comforte and courage; with what hope and expectation of victorie wee ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelues againſt theſe enemies of the Lord, abuſe not (I beſeech you) neither miſconſtrue mine exbortations. You will aſke peraduenture, how that may bee done. Uerely, what I haue ſayde,
<pb facs="tcp:20439:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>whatſoeuer I haue brought for your encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as I haue done it in ſimplicitie and ſingle meaning, grounding on the word of our God: ſo if any doe thinke that hue they well or ill, ſeeke they to knowe God aright or abide they in ignorance, they ſhall enioye the promiſes of the Scripture which I haue alledged, let ſuch knowe that theſe comfortes pertaine not to them. For I haue ſayd nothing, but that which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taining promiſe of helpe to them that are the true Church, both ſo farre ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to vs, as by embracing that true interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and profeſſion of Gods worde (which our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies are boyde of, and without which none are the choſen people of God) we declare our ſelues to be the true Church of Chriſt, as out of all queſtion our popiſh aduerſaries are not. To the entent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we may not glory in our profeſſion alone, crying the <hi>Temple of the Lorde, the Temple of the Lord</hi> is amongſt vs, and therfore to vs ſimply both al belong, obſerue (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as our profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter hope unto vs, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be aſſured to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile) 3. things neceſſarily to be performed of vs.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt is, <hi>that we truſt not in our own va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantnes or furniture to the battel but onely in the Lord.</hi> In this confidence little <hi>Dauid</hi> did ſet vppon the great Giaunt <hi>Goliath</hi> and preuailed. <hi>Thou commeſt to me</hi> (ſayth <hi>Dauid) with ſpeare &amp; ſhield, but I come to thee in the name of the Lord of hoſtes,</hi> that is to ſay, truſting in him are
<pb facs="tcp:20439:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>not in worldly weapons or defence. <hi>My hart tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the Lord</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Dauid) and I was holpen. Pſal. 28.9.</hi> Likewiſe the Prophet <hi>Hana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. 2. Chron. 16.</hi> teacheth vs the ſame leſſon. For ſpeaking vnto <hi>Aſa</hi> the King, he ſaith on this forte: <hi>Becauſe thou haſt reſted on the king of Aram and not truſted in the Lord thy God, therefore is the hoaſt of the king of Aram eſcaped out of thy hande. The Aethiopians and the Lutims were they not a great hoaſt with charrets and horſemen, yet becauſe thou diddeſt truſt in the Lord he deliuered them into thine hande.</hi> By all which we may perceiue how the Lord is readie to helpe them which truſt in him: as for ſuch as truſt in the arme of fleſh he giueth them ouer to the pray, or diſappoynteth them of the victorie which they hoped for, leaſt they might ſay, how they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed by the ſtrength of their owne hand. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs ſo prepare our ſelues to the battell, let vs ſo exerciſe the weapons of this earthly warfare that wee truſt not in them but in the Lorde, and no doubt our enemies ſhall fall before vs.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A ſecond thing required of vs in this caſe, is that we put away vngodlineſſe farre from vs, that wee repent vs of our ſinnes, and giue our ſelues to holineſſe of life, and a diligent following of the commaundements of God. This rule the Lorde teacheth vs, <hi>Deut. 32.9. When thou goeſt our with the hoaſt againſt thine enemies</hi> (ſayth the
<pb facs="tcp:20439:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord) <hi>keepe thee then from all wickedneſſe.</hi> So <hi>Leuit. 26.</hi> he promiſeth victorie to his people on this condition if they ſerue him. <hi>Keepe my Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>reuerence my ſanctuarie, walke in mine ordinaunces, keepe my commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then ſhall yee chaſe your enemies, and they ſhall fall before you vpon the ſworde.</hi> A. game, <hi>Deut. 11. If ye keepe diligently theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements no man ſhall ſtand againſt you.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>Deut. 28.7. If thou ſhalt obey dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently the voyce of the Lorde, and doe all his commaundements, the Lorde ſhall cauſe thine enemies that riſe againſt thee to fall before thy face.</hi> Conſider this (deerely beloued) for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and entent, that ye which feare the Lorde may haue confidence in the day of battell, and that ſuch as being appoynted in the behalfe of our countrie to goe againſt our enemies knowing this, may la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to reforme themſelues in knowledge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, before they ſet foote into the battell, leaſt there the vengeance of the Lord ouerthrowe them. It is thought of ſome wicked perſons, that to haue a payre of Dice in the one hand and a whore in the other, this is Souldierlike; but wo vnto ſuch, for theſe are poynts of vngodlineſſe, which muſt by all of them be put away which will bee aſſured to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper in battell againſt their enemies. Wee reade in the ſeuenth of <hi>Ioſua</hi> how <hi>Achan</hi> ſinned againſt the Lord in the excommunicate thing, for which cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:20439:23"/>three thouſand men of the hoaſt of <hi>Iſraell</hi> (though they were the onely true profeſſors of the world at that time) fled before the men of <hi>Ay,</hi> and the men of <hi>Ay</hi> ſmote of them vpon a thirtie and ſixe men: beware therefore that ye purge your ſelues before the fight, for the battell is the Lordes place of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and the enemies are his axe which he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in his hand, therewith to deſtroy all thoſe that with a ſtiffe necke and a rebellious heart goe on in breaking the commandements of the Lord. Some will ſay, what is this a rule for Souldiers onely? No verely, but for all generally as well as for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It ſtandeth euery one of vs vppon to amende that which is amiſſe in vs. The oppreſſor of the Lordes Prophetes, vnder what colour ſoeuer hee doth it, muſt take heede that he leaue; the blaſphemer of Gods name muſt now begin to hallowe it; the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerters of iudgement muſt now giue vpright ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; the robbers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church muſt now liue of their owne labors; the proud muſt now be humble; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liar muſt now ſpeak truth; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adulterer muſt now keepe his veſſell in holineſſe; the contemner of the worde muſt now begin to embrace it; the lukewarme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeller muſt now become zealous; yea euery Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate in his place, ſo farre as his authoritie will ſtretch in godlineſſe, muſt effectually looke to it, that ſinne be ſuppreſſed, ſo ſhall we proſper againſt theſe aduerſaries of ours.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The laſt thing which is required of vs in this
<pb facs="tcp:20439:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>caſe, is that according to the preſent occaſion mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, we reſorte daily and diligently vnto the Lord in humble and hartie prayer, deſiring the aſſiſtance of his mightie hand in the tune of neede and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie. This if we do (brethren) let us not thinke that the Lord will ſend us backe without comfort. For why his promiſe is, <hi>That if wee call vpon him in the time of trouble he will heare vs and deliuer vs. Pſal.50.15.</hi> and herevnto the manifolde exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Gods word giue teſtimonie. When <hi>Ioſua</hi> was gone out to fight againſt <hi>Amaleck, Moſes</hi> prayed earneſtly vnto the Lord in the behalfe of his people, and by this meanes the Lord gaue victorie to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo that <hi>Ioſua</hi> diſcomfited <hi>Amaleck</hi> and his people with the edge of the ſworde <hi>Exod. 17.</hi> When <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> in battell at <hi>Ramoth Gilead</hi> againſt the <hi>Aramites</hi> was in daunger to be ſtaine, he cried in prayer to the Lord, and the Lord cauſed the men of warre to departe from him. <hi>1 Reg. 22. 32.</hi> When <hi>Ietur</hi> and <hi>Naphiſh</hi> cried vuto God in battell he heard them, becauſe they truſted in him. <hi>1. Chron. 5.19.</hi> When <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was beſieged of the hoaſt of <hi>Senacherib, Ezekiah</hi> then King of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet ioyned together in prayer vnto the Lord, at whoſe petition, the <hi>Lord ſent an Angell which deſtroyed all the valiant men and the Princes &amp; Captaines of the hoaſt of the King of Aſhur, to the number of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred foureſcore &amp; fiue thouſand. 2. Chron. 32.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20439:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Among other, that is a moſt comfortable place which wée finde written <hi>Luc. 18.</hi> where the wicked Iudge which neither feared God nor reuerented man, though of long time he would not doe the poore widowe iuſtice againſt her aduerſarie, yet at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt becauſe of her importunitie he did her right: Whervpon our Sauiour concludeth, ſaying: <hi>And ſhall not God auenge his elect which crie vnto him day and night, yea though he ſuffer long for them, I tell you he will auenge them quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> You ſee (deerely beloued) how much the Lord regardeth the earneſt prayers of his children cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for helpe vnto him againſt their wicked aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. Let vs therefore neuer ceaſe, let vs put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God euery day the humble ſupplication of our harts for the reuenging of the blood of our brethren, which theſe popiſh <hi>Aramites</hi> haue ſtaine here, in <hi>Flanders,</hi> or els where; let vs be importunate with the poore widow and neuer giue ouer, till we haue aunſwer of comforte from the throne of the Lorde. He is not an harde harted or vnkinde, but a moſt mercifull father to them that lift vp pure harts and hands before him: he will not laugh at the teares of his children, but his compaſſion will be moued, and the fire of his ielouſie will burne and breake foorth againſt theſe our aduerſaries, who aſſault his ſpouſe and Church in England to enforce her to commit fornication with them, and to forſake that faithfull couenant which ſhe made with the
<pb facs="tcp:20439:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lorde. Thus ye ſee (deerely beloued) what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts the Lorde hath layd vp for them that profeſſe his trueth ſincerely, and that we alſo ſhall aſſuredly enioye them, if as wé ſhe we our ſelues by our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to be of that kingdome of Chriſt, which ſhal ſubdue all the kingdomes of the world, of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe Saincts which God hath promiſed to deliuer from the hands of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> ſo we truſt not in our owne ſtrength but in the Lorde on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; forſake our iniquities from the bottome of our hearts, and pray earneſtly to our heauenly father (not in the name of Saincts, as our aduerſaries doe) but in the name of Chriſt his only ſonne our Sauiour, to bee a tower of defence and a mercifull protectour vnto vs. God of his mercie graunt. &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Laus ſoli deo.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
